<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Blog Category:  Social Media | Jeremy's Programming Blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/social-media/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://www.jeremymorgan.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-30T12:51:07-07:00</updated>
  <id>https://www.jeremymorgan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeremy Morgan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Increase Your Klout Score]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/social-media/how-to-increase-your-klout-score/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-05T14:12:15-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/social-media/how-to-increase-your-klout-score</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>By now you've likely heard of Klout, it's the startup that aims to measure how much influence you have by giving you a "score" and showing the topics you are influential in. In this short article I will tell you how to increase your Klout score so you too can have a nice big number next to your name on Klout.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong>Want a Bigger Klout Score?</strong></p>

<p><a href="http://jeremymorgan.s3.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/klout-big.png"><img src="http://jeremymorgan.s3.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/klout-big.png" alt="How to increase your Klout score" /></a>There are people out there who really care about Klout and <a href="http://klout.com/#/jeremycmorgan">their Klout score</a>. There are rumors that companies do their hiring based on them. People charge for their services and tie that to their Klout score. So to some people it's clearly important. If you found this page and are reading this it's likely important to you too. So you want to know how to raise it?</p>

<blockquote><p>Stop spending all your time on Klout and start putting content out there.</p></blockquote>

<p>That's really all there is to it. Instead of spending so much time trading +k with people, cruising websites and forums looking for trades, purchasing likes and retweets, just produce more content. That's really the secret.</p>

<p>All the time you spend trying to game the site is time you could be spending writing on your blog, or finding great content to post on Google+, Twitter or Facebook. The people with the highest Klout scores are generally people who aren't even members of Klout at all. Think about it, do you really think people like Linus Torvalds and Seth Godin are spending hours obsessing over their Klout score? No, of course not! They're busy doing what they do and their work is bringing in an audience.</p>

<p><strong>How You Should Actually be Using Klout.</strong></p>

<p>In the interest of full disclosure, I use Klout. I do +k trades with people and participate on the website. Why? Because it's a great way to meet people. I actually met some people from Empire Avenue in the Klout trading rooms that are really cool and have a lot of good stuff to share. I have found influencers and been added as an influencer by others and met a lot of people that way.</p>

<blockquote><p>If you use Klout as a networking tool you'll get far more use from it.</p></blockquote>

<p>Use Klout as just another networking tool to meet new people, don't use it as a place to show off. Their algorithm is flawed anyway, and if you game it too much your score will likely drop. But if you use it as a way of meeting new people, you may be inspired to do something new, or find someone who will share your work.</p>

<p><strong>The Bottom Line</strong></p>

<p>In other words, the best way to get a high Klout score is to ignore it completely, and try to be more influential in your field by adding to a body of work, not by trading +k with people for hours.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Disqus is Going To Change the Web]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/social-media/how-disqus-is-going-to-change-the-web/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-19T19:47:30-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/social-media/how-disqus-is-going-to-change-the-web</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The web has had a problem since the early days that's just starting to get solved now. People want to talk back and they want to be heard. They also like joining communities and participating them, especially now. In the last ten years it's possible for the average person to have created hundreds, if not thousands of separate accounts on different websites. Wouldn't it be nice to just have one or two accounts to use everywhere?</p>

<h3><a href="http://jeremymorgan.s3.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/disqus.jpg"><img src="http://jeremymorgan.s3.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/disqus.jpg" alt="disqus comments" /></a>What Disqus has done</h3>

<p>If you haven't seen Disqus around, you will. It's spreading to sites all over the place, and as of today I installed it on this one. What Discus has done is create a sort of single sign on for websites. You can make a comment on this site if you have an account on:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Google (Gmail)</p></li>
<li><p>Facebook</p></li>
<li><p>Twitter</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Who doesn't have at least one of those? In the past people had to create accounts everywhere, and the simple fact is nobody wants to do that. <strong>People have to really love your site, and be very compelled to discuss things with others, to create an account on it.</strong></p>

<p>Nobody wants to remember 1000 accounts, and people don't want to give their email address to every site in the world, especially if they just want to make a comment and leave.</p>

<p>Discus has now connected them so you can log in to many websites with accounts you already use. This is so incredibly convenient and simple it's amazing it wasn't done years ago.</p>

<h3>How Disqus changes things:</h3>

<p>If this service takes off the web is going to be a different, better place. Here's why:</p>

<p><strong>1. More people will participate</strong></p>

<p>Because they already have an account at one of these services, it it could be seconds to log in and make a comment. Once someone has decided to do this, they're logged in whenever they visit another site with Disqus comments too. The people who have something to say but would never dream of creating an account on your blog (or don't know how) will gladly post a comment if it's made really easy. You're rolling out the welcome mat for everyone and inviting them to your site.</p>

<p><strong>2. People will be nicer </strong></p>

<p>****If people commenting have some accountability the chances of them acting foolish diminishes greatly. Think about it, if you have a "badboy69" profile with fake info and a picture of a middle finger you can pretty much say anything you want and act inappropriately without it affecting you much in real life. You would say and do things you wouldn't really do offline. But if your comments are tied to your REAL name, photo, school, employer, friends etc are you really going to act out of line? It acts as sort of a jerk filter on your site and someone could create a fake profile on Facebook and comment but the amount of people willing to do that are reduced. I think you'll see more rational, respectable comments.</p>

<p><strong>3. You'll have people seeking reputation</strong></p>

<p>****This ties into #2 slightly in that people will be more conscious of their image and reputation as they are posting. When all of my posts say "Jeremy Morgan" and have my smiling mug next to them you can bet I'm going to think about my reputation more. Do I want to post this? Is it helpful? Am I contributing positively here or just making a mess? These are things people think about more when their reputation is on the line. When people care about things like this they tend to make better decisions and contributions when posting something. You will get people willing to jump in and help.</p>

<p><strong>4. You will take advantage of herd theory
</strong></p>

<p><strong> </strong>Surely by now you've figured out the great forum/discussion problem as a webmaster. Nobody will comment on your stuff if nobody is commenting. Nobody is going to sign up for a forum if there is nobody on the forum, it's an endless cycle that's very hard to break out of. When it's made this easy more people will comment. When more people comment, others see that and decide to jump in too. Soon people are spreading the links and talking about your site. More people on your site will lead to bigger improvement to said sites. <strong>By actively promoting engagement websites can improve and evolve for the better.</strong></p>

<p><strong>5. It will reduce spam</strong></p>

<p>This one is one of the best benefits yet. Twenty dollar automated bots can create accounts and spam WordPress sites with ease. Every time I log into my panel I see another 100 or so comments left by spammers. They can do this with Disqus too, it's just more difficult. Not only do they have to create an account on Facebook / Gmail / Twitter but they also have to take an extra step of connecting through Disqus as well before commenting. Also it doesn't appear that links posted in Disqus comments can pass any link juice (though I don't know that for sure) so that would eliminate some motivation to spam. ( Spammers don't post links on forums for the traffic, they're usually doing it for the backlinks to game search engines).</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>So after consideration I think that if Disqus takes off, we all win. From what I can see it's being adopted all over the place and I hope this trend continues. It's nice to have one login you can carry around with you and use everywhere and I'm sorry but OpenID is not easy enough for the average web surfer. I really hope this site takes off, if you have commenting on your site you should really consider it. You can even migrate all your old posts to it.</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://disqus.com/">Disqus website</a></p>

<p><a href="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/disqus-comment-system/">Disqus for WordPress</a> (or you can just add it through plugins)</p>

<p>Have fun and leave a comment!</p>

<p>_ Note: This is not a paid endorsement of this service. I have not been paid or compensated in any way, and have had no contact with Disqus before doing this article. This is 100% my opinion only and I want to disclose that here._</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Five Reasons Why I'm not giving up on Google+]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/social-media/five-reasons-why-im-not-giving-up-on-google/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-10T14:37:48-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/social-media/five-reasons-why-im-not-giving-up-on-google</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://jeremymorgan.s3.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/reasons-to-use-google-plus.jpg"></p>

<p>Google+ was launched in June of last year and was poised to be "the Facebook killer". Naturally that didn't happen and people are already sounding the death knell for Google+ due to slow adaptation and abandonment. But I'm not ready to give up on Google+ yet, as a marketer or as a user, and I'll give you some reasons why.</p>

<p>I'd like to start by saying I don't think it will kill or take over Facebook. It has permeated nearly every part of our society and it's widely adopted by a lot of people.</p>

<p>Myspace almost had this level of critical mass, but it was seen as "cheesy" and more of a kids thing than something serious. Facebook doesn't have that problem so they achieved a higher adoption than Myspace ever did. It would take a lot of factors for Google+ to beat Facebook, basically Facebook would have to mess up really bad, and consistently, and Google would have to blow us away with great features. I don't see that happening anytime soon.</p>

<p>But here's why I'm not giving up on Google+:</p>

<h3>1. It's Google</h3>

<p>I would never say Google is too big to fail, but they do have some considerable clout and have the resources to build great products. While the public has been slow to embrace it they're still using the gmail service and Facebook as two separate entities, and the idea of having just one is very appealing. So far Facebook has dominated social media and failed at an attempt at email, while Google has dominated email and failed at attempts at social media. Facebook might be winning but if I were a betting man, I'd bet on the incredibly innovative search giant before the popularity machine.</p>

<h3>2. It's integrated with all my Google Services</h3>

<p><img class="left" src="http://jeremymorgan.s3.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/how-many-users-google-plus-300x186.jpg"> I use a lot of Google services frequently. I use Gmail and Google chat, and use my Android phone to use both. Analytics, Google Drive, Documents, etc. So Google+ is just a natural step for me, it's very easy and convenient. The problem is there is hardly anyone there. But reading Google+ postings and putting up my own is easy to do from one place. Also my email contacts are ported in which is very convenient.</p>

<h3>3. Its more fun to use</h3>

<p>The first time I tried Linux, I remember it feeling a bit uncomfortable, because I was used to Windows. But then when I got the hang of it I ended up liking it a lot better. Now I only power into Windows when I absolutely need it because I like the "feel" of Linux. This is exactly how I am about Google+. I just like the interface and "feel" of it. It's more readable, seems to be much faster and it hasn't been taken over by stupid requests for *ville games and the like. Sharing information is easy, sparks is kinda cool and circles is a lot easier than the Facebook equivalent.</p>

<h3>4. The crowd is a little smarter</h3>

<p>Are there smart people on Facebook? Of course, but let's face it everyone is on Facebook and not everyone is a Genius. I've noticed that the people who use Google+ seem to be a bit more hip, more intelligent and better behaved than the Facebook crowd. Even the professionals I follow for Programming and SEO seem to post a lot more stuff on Google+, and interact more. Maybe Facebook is just destined to become the same digital ghetto that myspace is, but i see a lot more stuff on there that I simply don't see on Google+. Call me a jerk, elitist or whatever it's just a better neighborhood.</p>

<h3>5. There is an SEO Benefit coming for Google+ users</h3>

<p>Now this part is pure speculation on my part, but I have a feeling Google Authorship is going to be a huge shift this year. The articles you write on your blog and elsewhere can be tied to your Google+ profile (and i recommend it)and this allows you to make sure that content on the net that you create is attributed to your identity. I have a theory that this identity is going to be used as a factor when ranking said articles. How many people follow you, vote up your content and how you respond to your audience will all be factored in to this part of the algorithm.</p>

<p>I don't think Google will be boosting up your site just because you use Google+, but I think a well respected author with authority will certainly be seeing a boost from his or her content with this addition. Again all speculation but I'm sure I'm right.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>I almost gave up on Google+ but I've recently come back to it, and really enjoy it. I try to update it regularly and hope to build a good audience I can chat with like i do on Twitter and Facebook. From a marketing point of view I think it would be somewhat tough to sell stuff on Google+, but of course it's possible. A better goal for most people would probably be to shoot for improving their brand awareness and customer interactions with Google+.</p>

<p>As a casual user I don't want to give it up because there is so much good info posted on it, I find great stuff every day. If you want, <a href="https://plus.google.com/+JeremyMorgan">follow me or add me to a circle</a>! See you there!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Remove Annoying Apps From Facebook]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/social-media/how-to-remove-annoying-apps-from-facebook/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-05T06:36:34-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/social-media/how-to-remove-annoying-apps-from-facebook</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you get 1000 requests a day for your birthday or an invite to (something)ville? Rather than asking all your friends to stop sending them, just block the app. It's easier than you think.</p>

<p>What you do is click on the notification and "show all". This shows a full list of all your notifications (messages, app requests, everything).</p>

<p><a href="http://jeremymorgan.s3.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/how-to-remove-annoying-apps-facebook.jpg"><img src="http://jeremymorgan.s3.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/how-to-remove-annoying-apps-facebook.jpg" alt="How to Remove Annoying Apps from Facebook" /></a>Hover your mouse over the end of each row until you see an "x" button. It will say "remove" on the hover text, but click the X.</p>

<p><a href="http://jeremymorgan.s3.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/how-to-remove-annoying-apps-facebook-2.jpg"><img src="http://jeremymorgan.s3.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/how-to-remove-annoying-apps-facebook-2.jpg" alt="How to Remove Annoying Apps from Facebook" /></a></p>

<p>Click on Change app settings.</p>

<p><a href="http://jeremymorgan.s3.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/how-to-remove-annoying-apps-facebook-3.jpg"><img src="http://jeremymorgan.s3.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/how-to-remove-annoying-apps-facebook-3.jpg" alt="How to Remove Annoying Apps from Facebook" /></a></p>

<p>Then in this window select "Never".</p>

<p>That's it! You can block all these apps and minimize your notifications to ones you actually care about. It's far easier than asking your friends to stop it.</p>

<p>Hope this helps!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Twitter and Facebook can help SEO - But how? ]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/social-media/twitter-and-facebook-can-help-seo-but-how/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-09T11:47:30-08:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/social-media/twitter-and-facebook-can-help-seo-but-how</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's been confirmed by Bing and Google that Twitter and Facebook can help your search rankings. This is something SEOs have speculated about and known for quite some time. But how does it really affect your rankings?</p>

<p><strong>Social Search vs Web Search</strong></p>

<p>There is a distinction here that should be noted. When <a href="http://www.bing.com/social/search?q=Justin+Bieber&amp;go=&amp;form=DTPSOH">doing a search on Bing Social</a>, you can see what people are saying on various social media sites, mainly Twitter and YouTube. The links in those results go to either a page showing where the term was mentioned, or the profile of the person saying it. This is a social search only, Google has a similar feature that's tied to your <a href="http://www.google.com/profiles/jeremy.morgan">Google Profile</a>. Some social searches show up at the bottom of web searches also.</p>

<p>Web searches of course are just <a href="http://www.bing.com/search?q=Justin+Bieber&amp;go=&amp;form=QBLH&amp;qs=n&amp;sk=&amp;sc=8-10">standard searches of the web</a>, which is what we want to capitalize on. So how do they relate?</p>

<p><strong>Once again, authority is king. </strong></p>

<p>Both Google and Bing have confirmed that these social results do factor into your web results as well. Any guesses as to what they might focus on? If you guessed "Authority" you're probably right. A solid tenet of good SEO is becoming an influencer. Reputation is everything and when Google sees that your site is an authority on a subject matter it's treated well. If your site is one that others link to frequently and is shown to influence a niche, your rankings go up. Social search is no different.</p>

<p>If your links are frequently "liked" on FaceBook and your tweets are often retweeted, you'll show up more in Social Search, but it's also likely the links you post you will get some SEO juice as well. As many of you know, Twitter links are <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nofollow">nofollow</a> links, but it looks like they'll still factor in. IF you are someone who has "authority" on Twitter you can expect some of your links to get some juice.</p>

<p><strong>How do I take advantage of it? </strong></p>

<p>The answer to this one is pretty simple, and something I preach constantly on this site: make something worth going to. Give out content people want, and they will follow. If you have a Twitter account that just posts constant links to your website, or you're constantly hawking affiliate links people won't follow you. But if you post valuable, entertaining or remarkable content, they will. And with a good Twitter or Facebook following you can get an extra kick to your search engine rankings as well.</p>

<p>A black hat solution of course would be to create some fake networks. You could create 1,000 twitter accounts and get a ring going where a bunch of the accounts retweet your links all over, and you could do the same with Facebook. And I'm sure it would probably work fairly well for a while, but they'll have a detection method for it, if they don't already. As I like to advise my clients, black hat SEO works, and often works well but it's a poor long term business plan. Set your goals accordingly.</p>

<p>Some more reading on this subject:</p>

<p><a href="http://searchengineland.com/what-social-signals-do-google-bing-really-count-55389">What Social Signals do Bing and Google really count?</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.socialtimes.com/2010/12/facebook-and-twitter-affect-seo-confirmed-by-google-and-bing/">Facebook and Twitter affect SEO</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.seomoz.org/blog/google-bing-confirm-twitter-facebook-influence-seo">Google and Bing confirm Twitter and Facebook affect SEO</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
