<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Blog Category:  Marketing | Jeremy's Programming Blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/marketing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://www.jeremymorgan.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-30T12:51:07-07:00</updated>
  <id>https://www.jeremymorgan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeremy Morgan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What We Can Learn From Caine's Arcade]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/marketing/what-we-can-learn-from-caines-arcade/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-17T17:03:27-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/marketing/what-we-can-learn-from-caines-arcade</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>By now you've likely seen the short film by Nirvan Mullick titled "Caine's Arcade" about 9 year old Caine Monroy and the arcade he created from cardboard boxes in his dad's parts store, as it has went globally viral in the last week. So what can we as Internet Marketers learn from this kid? A lot.</p>

<p>If you haven't seen the video, <a href="http://www.cainesarcade.com/">watch it here</a>. It's the best 10 minutes you'll spend online all year. The story is very simple: a boy hanging out with his dad at work gets bored and starts creating an arcade, and immerses himself in it. Nobody shows up to the arcade and he has a hard time talking people into playing. One day Nirvan, a Los Angeles filmmaker who appears to know media pretty well, shows up to buy a part for his car and sees this elaborate arcade, and decides to play. Then comes the moment that will change both of their lives.</p>

<p>As Internet Marketers we should all be paying attention very closely here. Here are a few things we can learn from Caine and his story:</p>

<h3>1. Never Give Up</h3>

<p>This one is fairly obvious, but is a huge part of this story. At first, nobody was showing up at this kid's arcade. He was begging people to come play and was being ignored. Did he quit? Of course not, he kept building and adding on to it. He acted as if he had hundreds of customers to answer to and kept plugging away at it, adding and changing, even though nobody was there. This kid figured out a secret to success that many adults have yet to grasp. He simply refused to give up and take the easy way out.</p>

<h3>2. Put yourself in the customer's shoes</h3>

<p>One thing I noticed right away was this: Caine didn't talk about how much money he wanted to make. He talked about the differences between plays and fun pass, but he didn't focus on money or treat it as a goal. He focused on bringing people entertainment and fun. He played the games, improved them and thought about them. Rather than obsess over the money he wanted to make he obsessed over his product. He thought of the customer before anything else and really imagined what they wanted. He's a younger Steve Jobs, obsessing over every tiny detail of the customer experience.</p>

<h3>3. Act as if you're already successful.</h3>

<p>The one thing I noticed was before the flash mob incident Caine was being interviewed about the arcade, and talking about what people playing would say or think. The reality at the time was: there were no people. Caine had it set in his mind that people were going to show up, and worked and innovated as if his arcade were full of customers already. He designed games as if there were a line of people waiting outside to see what he was going to do next (there wasn't). Yet he didn't care, he trudged on and kept working on his product</p>

<p>When the crowds showed up, he was ready.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://jeremymorgan.s3.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/caines-arcade.jpg" title="What we can learn from Caine's arcade" ></p>

<h3>4. Don't worry about what others may think.</h3>

<p>Many kids his age would love to do something like this, but most would be afraid to. I'll freely admit that at nine years old I wouldn't have done something like this out of a fear of rejection, or being made fun of for it. Caine didn't care, no matter what people thought of what he was doing, he continued on doing what he knew was right. If there were detractors he wasn't deterred by them.</p>

<h3>5. Hard work still pays off.</h3>

<p>Did you notice the part where his father asks if he wants to go home for the day, as they are coming back from the pizza parlor? Without pause Caine says "no can do". He's determined to get back to work on his passion. It's an amazing thing to see. Couple that with the fact that this kid spent months working and building this thing and waiting for people to show up. That's an attention span you just don't see anymore.</p>

<h3>6. It's not about getting rich</h3>

<p>When you're passionate about what you do, money is not the primary goal. When you hear Caine talk about the fun pass you get it: he's trying to hook you in. He's trying to entertain you. It's not about getting $2 instead of $1 its about getting people to try his games and be entertained. When you see the smile on his face as he's running things you quickly realize this isn't about the money it's about passion. Who cares if you get rich when you're doing what you love?</p>

<h3>7. Don't talk about what you are going to do, just do it.</h3>

<p>This kid could have sat around staring at the floor and wishing he would have an arcade someday. He could have told his friends "when I grow up...." but he just couldn't wait that long. Instead he took a leap and just started DOING what needed to be done. This kind of fearless bold attitude is what separates the talkers from the doers. Caine is obviously a doer.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://jeremymorgan.s3.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/caines-arcade-2.jpg"></p>

<h3>8. Innovation is essential (and sometimes free).</h3>

<p>Caine showed a lot of innovation in his work. He saw that the soccer game was too easy so he changed it to make it harder. He wanted a claw machine so he made one. He created a checksum to validate a fun pass (pure genius by the way) and mostly used his imagination to improve his product. It cost him nothing more than imagination and time.</p>

<h3>9. Utilize what you have.</h3>

<p>The materials to make Caine's games were boxes from his dad's store and other items he found around there, and some of his prizes were his old toys. He took inventory of what he wanted to do, and what he had available to him and made them meet in the middle. Rather than wait for things to happen, he made them happen with what he had.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://jeremymorgan.s3.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/caines-arcade-3.jpg"></p>

<h3>10. Make no excuses.</h3>

<p>This kid wouldn't have to look far to find reasons to quit. He didn't have even a single arcade game at his disposal, had very few tools and little budget. He's just a 9 year old kid from East L.A. who doesn't appear to come from a rich family (though it appears his father has given him something far more valuable than money) and nobody would question him for a second about giving up. But as we know that wasn't really an option for him. Rather than find the reasons he couldn't do something he found ways to do it. Instead of complaining and blaming everyone else for his problems he buckled down and made it happen. Even when nobody showed up he still kept going as if it didn't matter.</p>

<p>The term "pulling yourself up by your own bootstraps" was made for people like Caine.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>It's amazing how much you can learn from 10 minutes of video, and how much you can be inspired by a 9 year old boy with a dream. Caine has earned fame, appearances and a six figure college fund. He deserves every single bit of it. He showed heart and passion you don't often see in children or even adults these days. He had a vision and worked to make it happen. He's got a very bright future ahead of him.</p>

<p>What are you waiting for?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Real Secret to Success on the Web]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/marketing/the-real-secret-to-success-on-the-web/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-12T18:35:01-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/marketing/the-real-secret-to-success-on-the-web</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The inspiration for this article started with a discussion I was having about successful blogs and websites.  From that I started thinking, and composed a tweet:</p>

<blockquote><p>Want to succeed? Don't kiss ass, get walked on, hold your tongue or follow the crowd. Disrupt. Offend. Stand Out. Achieve.</p></blockquote>

<p>I got to thinking: this really is the silver bullet for a successful blog. In fact, it's a secret to success in general. Nobody ever made a difference by following the crowd and doing what everyone was doing. So why do so many people follow this plan when they start a blog?</p>

<p>If you really want your site to take off, you have to stand out.  You have to have opinions and be ready to share them. You have to rock the boat, shake the cage and really put yourself up for scrutiny. You need to interact with people and be honest with them. Instead of worrying what everyone else is going to think, focus on what YOU think and why.</p>

<p>This is the real secret of success for the web, when it comes down to the brass tacks.</p>

<p>Some other things to consider:</p>

<ul>
<li>Give people content they want.  Ask, then listen.</li>
<li>Don't be afraid to disagree with someone, even an industry expert.</li>
<li>Don't be afraid of offending people with your opinion.</li>
<li>Don't be afraid to take an unpopular stance.</li>
<li>Don't be afraid to be the first to try something.</li>
<li>Interact with others in the field.</li>
<li>Instead of fawning over celebrities and experts online, challenge them with good questions.</li>
<li>Keep your eye on your prize.</li>
</ul>


<p>If you try to build something that everyone likes you'll fail.  Don't worry about anyone else, just create. Let your personality shine through and do what you want to do. The more you enjoy it the better you'll do at it.</p>

<p>Stop making excuses, get out there and do it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We didn't even see it coming.]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/marketing/we-didnt-even-see-it-coming/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-17T18:10:33-07:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/marketing/we-didnt-even-see-it-coming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some of the best ideas, and some of the greatest creations of the world have come by accident. Many large successful projects started out as something small, and nobody ever dreamed it would "blow up" like it did. This is something marketers and entrepreneurs don't give a lot of thought to.</p>

<p>I could name a million examples of things that started really small and grew into worldwide phenomenons, but I'll only mention a few.</p>

<p><strong>Linux</strong> - A 21 year old college student in Finland decides to write his own copy of Minix, an operating system for his computer and give it away for free. Just "dabbling around" at first, 20 years later his project has computing as we know it. (I'm typing this on a laptop running Linux in fact, and this website sits on a Linux server).</p>

<p><strong>Facebook</strong> - A story many more people are familiar with, in 2003 a college student decides to create a website for Harvard students to share information about themselves and what they're doing. Today it has over 750 million users. As a side note, here is what CNN had to say about Facebook in 2006:</p>

<blockquote><p>Last spring, Facebook reportedly turned down a $750 million buyout offer, holding out instead for as much as $2 billion. Bad move. After selling itself to Rupert Murdoch's Fox for $580 million last year, MySpace is now the Web's second most popular website. Facebook is growing too - but given that MySpace has quickly grown into the industry's 80-million-user gorilla, it's hard to imagine who would pay billions for an also-ran.</p></blockquote>

<p>We have the benefit of hindsight now, but even 5 years ago it was hard to predict the rise of Facebook.</p>

<p><strong>Apple</strong> -A couple of geeks messing around in a garage decide to build their own personal computer - something unheard of at the time. Little did they know they'd change the world.</p>

<p>This kind of stuff happens all the time, in fact here is a list of  <a href="http://www.businesspundit.com/fortune-500-rags-to-riches/">Fortune 500 Companies that started with nothing</a>.</p>

<p><strong>So what's my point?</strong></p>

<p>What these examples all have in common is this: there was a need, and by filling that need, they discovered many other people with the same need. They didn't set out to change the world, but that's exactly what happened. They only thought of filling their own needs, in a small world that suddenly outgrew them. If you start out with the idea of making it big, raking in millions and then finding a way to do it, you're working backwards. This is probably why so many of these ventures fail.</p>

<p>Instead of finding a way to strike it rich, think of a need that you can fulfill. It's not true that everything that needs to be invented is already here. There is plenty of need out there, you just have to find it. If you're the one solving a problem, and many others have that problem, you'll find yourself in high demand.</p>

<p>Think about it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Charlie Sheen Strategy]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/marketing/the-charlie-sheen-strategy/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-07T06:20:30-08:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/marketing/the-charlie-sheen-strategy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you haven't heard or read the name "Charlie Sheen" last week, congratulations on managing to seal yourself away from all media. His very public breakdown has been all everyone is talking about. His all out, reckless self promotion is working great, but is it a good business approach?</p>

<h3>Better to Burn Out Than Fade Away</h3>

<p>The famous line from Kurt Cobain's suicide note (and taken from a Def Leppard song) is no doubt the approach Charlie is taking. He's outrageous, in your face and no holds barred. He's talking to anyone who will listen and saying the most shocking things he can think of, while flaunting his rock star lifestyle.</p>

<p>There is  no doubt he started this run already famous, with decades of movies and a hit TV show under his belt, but now he's in the news and on the web daily. He's the hot topic, and growing hotter.</p>

<p>But is this an approach YOU can take with your company or brand?</p>

<p>Can you be outrageous, offensive and reckless?</p>

<p>Will it work?</p>

<h3>Charlie Sheen as a business strategy.</h3>

<p>There is no doubt he's cashing in on this latest trainwreck of a media frenzy he's caused. You could do the same if you wanted. You can be outrageous, over the top, offensive and out of control. You can create viral videos of yourself doing something incredibly stupid with your website on your back. You could do something incredibly offensive, and your enemies will advertise for you.</p>

<p>You can pull out all the stops and do whatever it takes to become famous. Your company or brand can be the trending topic on Twitter and you could get bloggers to go crazy talking about you, and you too would cash in. You could make giant piles of money cashing in on this instant fame.</p>

<p>But what about next month, when they've forgotten about you? What about next year? These waves never truly last, and it's hard to keep people's attention for long. What will you do then? Will you take the pile of cash and make something else work? Will anyone care?</p>

<p>When you're infamous, the only thing people remember long term is the bad. The negative things associated with you will stay. Your credibility will be shot. Not only will people fail to take you seriously, they won't trust you. You can no longer hold your head up high and have people look up to you. A turnaround is always possible, but very difficult to do.</p>

<p>Is this what you really want for your company, and your brand? Are you doing things just to get attention that you could regret later?  Is your reputation worth it?</p>

<p>Think about it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Find the Edges.]]></title>
    <link href="https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/marketing/find-the-edges/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-23T20:21:11-08:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/marketing/find-the-edges</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>"Everything that can be invented has been invented"  -Charles Duell, Commissioner of US Patent Office, 1899</p></blockquote>

<p>Surely you've ran across this quote before, and probably had a laugh about it.  And since he likely didn't tweet this from his iPhone while driving his Smart Car, he was also wrong. But his quote has some truth to it today. Everything we realistically want and need is here. Of course there will be some breakthrough products that change the way we do things, but for the most part we're a pretty satisfied bunch. Succeeding in business is tougher than ever, because everything we need is already here, for the most part. So how to we move forward?</p>

<p>Statements like this are the type that people laugh about 5 years later. But realistically the odds that you are going to come up with a breakthrough invention that's completely new are pretty slim. You may come up with an improvement on a product or idea, sure but are you likely to come up with something that's completely, 100% out of this world new? Probably not. I'm not trying to be a Debbie Downer, just being realistic. So what can you to do to break ahead? You need to find an edge, a need that is unsatisfied.</p>

<p><strong>Example: Firefox</strong></p>

<p>The first Web browser was pretty awesome, and easy to market. It's 1993 and you want to check out these new "webpages" so you downloaded Mosiac, for free. Then along came Netscape who improved on the idea, and never made any real money. Microsoft, who was pretty late to the game, came out with Internet Explorer (also free) and changed the game again. Soon, IE took over the market and that was the end of the story, for quite a while. People didn't need anything more than Internet Explorer provided. They were happy. When the masses are happy with a product, they stick with it. No need for anything new.</p>

<p>But to say everyone was happy with IE would be false. There were security issues, and more technical users found problems with it. Developers hated it, because they had to change their code to "IE specific" pages and it was quite difficult to build standardized pages that looked the same to everyone. But these people, were they the status quo? Of course not. These were the "edge cases", the fringe groups, not the general user. Susie Soccer Mom didn't care about HTML and CSS standards when she was browsing Ebay for Beanie Babies so it didn't matter much. The edge was ignored for quite sometime.</p>

<p>Enter Firefox. This was a browser based on an entirely different engine, and built for the power user. Not only was it faster, but also more secure, and rendered pages better. It quickly caught on with the power users and development started really picking up, and Firefox quickly added support for plugins, themes, and other really great features. The power users tried it, adopted it and never looked back. The type of people who use Firefox are the type of people who try new things, and experiment. Again, they're on the edge. Today, Firefox is the second most used browser in the world, which is no small feat. David truly is throwing some serious rocks at Goliath, and they know it.</p>

<p>There are similar stories out there for Linux, MacOSX and other products that serve a minority rather than the majority. Make no mistake: <strong>If Firefox had tried to grab the mass market from IE they would have failed. </strong>If they tried to put out a "vanilla" product to compete with the existing vanilla product and go after the mass market, they would have failed. Instead, they found an edge.</p>

<p><strong>Summary</strong></p>

<p>So long story short, instead of trying to usurp some giant corporation's mass market product, look for the edges. Don't try to invent a better web browser, operating system or smart phone. You aren't going to start a revolution by inventing an a better lawn sprinkler.<strong> Don't try to come up with a better flavor of vanilla. The products that everyone wants are already here.</strong> The mass market products are already serving the masses just fine. Your product may be better, but they will ignore it. You have to shoot for the products that certain people want, and find the areas that the vanilla products aren't serving well.</p>

<p>Find an edge, and give it all you've got. Find a niche of a market that isn't being served well, and solve their problems. Not everyone is going to want your Caramel Apple and Cinnamon ice cream, but if you do it right, those who will want it will become loyal customers.</p>

<p>Remember as a marketer your job is to solve a problem. If your market is content, any small improvements will likely be ignored.  Find the market with problems.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
